Joseph L. Rauh Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Joseph L. Rauh Papers 1913-2008 1950-1984
MSS62041
Rauh, Joseph L., Jr., 1911-1992
110,000 items
301 containers
120.2 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Lawyer, civil rights activist, and civil libertarian of Washington, D.C. Chiefly legal files together with correspondence, memoranda, minutes of meetings, oral history interviews, speeches, writings, subject files, appointment books, and other papers relating to Rauh's career as a public interest lawyer handling cases pertaining to civil rights, civil liberties, and labor disputes. Includes files relating to his activities with Americans for Democratic Action and to his participation in Hubert H. Humphrey's presidential campaign in 1960.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Auerbach, Carl A. (Carl Abraham), 1915- --Correspondence.; Brennan, William J., 1906-1997--Correspondence.; Cardozo, Benjamin N. (Benjamin Nathan), 1870-1938--Correspondence.; Cohen, Benjamin V.--Correspondence.; Douglas, Paul H. (Paul Howard), 1892-1976--Correspondence.; Frankfurter, Felix, 1882-1965--Correspondence.; Greenberg, Jack, 1924-2016--Correspondence.; Hellman, Lillian, 1905-1984--Correspondence.; Henry, Aaron, 1922-1997--Correspondence.; Hollander, Edward D. (Edward Drey), 1908- --Correspondence.; Humphrey, Hubert H. (Hubert Horatio), 1911-1978--Correspondence.; Humphrey, Hubert H. (Hubert Horatio), 1911-1978.; Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973--Correspondence.; Kennedy, Edward M. (Edward Moore), 1932-2009--Correspondence.; Loeb, James I. (James Isaac), 1908- --Correspondence.; McCarthy, Eugene J., 1916-2005--Correspondence.; Miller, Arthur, 1915-2005--Correspondence.; Monroe, Marilyn, 1926-1962.; Orlikow, Velma.; Rauh, Joseph L., Jr., 1911-1992.; Remington, William Walter, 1917-1954--Trials, litigation, etc.; Reuther, Walter, 1907-1970--Correspondence.; Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1884-1962--Correspondence.; Schlesinger, Arthur M., Jr. (Arthur Meier), 1917-2007--Correspondence.; Wechsler, James A. (James Arthur), 1915-1983--Correspondence.; Wilkins, Roy, 1901-1981--Correspondence.; Yablonski, Joseph A. (Joseph Andrew), 1941- --Correspondence.
Organizations
Americans for Democratic Action.; Brotherhood of Sleeping Car Porters.; Democratic Party (U.S.); International Union, United Automobile Workers of America (A.F. of L.); International Union, United Automobile Workers of America (CIO); Mississippi Freedom Democratic Party.; United States. Congress. House. Committee on Un-American Activities.; United States. Supreme Court.
Subjects
Affirmative action programs--United States.; Automobile industry workers--Labor unions.; Civil rights--United States.; Communism.; Filibusters (Political science)--United States.; Labor disputes--United States.; Labor unions--United States.; Liberalism--United States.; National security--United States.; Patriotism--United States.; Political campaigns--United States.; Political parties--Mississippi.; Practice of law--Washington (D.C.); Public interest law--United States.; Trials (Perjury)--United States.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975.
Places
Mississippi--Politics and government--1951-; United States--Economic policy--20th century.; United States--Foreign relations--20th century.; United States--Politics and government--20th century.; Washington (D.C.)--Politics and government.
Occupations
Civil libertarians.; Civil rights leaders.; Lawyers.
Acquisition Information
The papers of Joseph L. Rauh, lawyer, civil libertarian, and civil rights activist, were given to the Library of Congress by Rauh in 1986. Subsequent additions were received from 1987 through 2015 from Rauh; his law associates, James C. Turner and Elliot C. Lichtman; his wife, Olie Rauh; and Rauh's sons, Carl Rauh and Michael Rauh.
Additional Guides
A description of the Rauh Papers appears in Library of Congress Acquisitions: Manuscript Division, 1987: 15-19.
Transfers
Sound recordings have been transferred to the Library's Motion Picture, Broadcasting and Recorded Sound Division where they are identified as part of these papers.
Related Material
Other papers held by the Library with material relating to Rauh are the Brotherhood of Sleeping Car Porter Records and the William Walter Remington Papers.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1911, Jan. 3 Born, Cincinnati, Ohio
1932 B.S., Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass.
1935 LL.B., Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass. Counsel to Securities and Exchange Commission Married Olie Westheimer
1936 1939 Law secretary, Supreme Court justices Benjamin N. Cardozo and Felix Frankfurter
1939 1942 Counsel, Department of Labor, Federal Communications Commission, Lend-Lease Administration, and Office for Emergency Management
1942 1945 Served on Douglas MacArthur's staff in the United States Army in Southwest Pacific; awarded Legion of Merit and Philippine Distinguished Service Star
1946 1947 General deputy housing expediter, Veterans Emergency Housing Program
1947 One of the founders of the Americans for Democratic Action (ADA); chairman of its executive committee, 1947-1952
1947 1986 Practiced law, Washington, D.C.
1952 1955 Vice chairman, Americans for Democratic Action (ADA)
1955 1957 Chairman, Americans for Democratic Action (ADA)
1992, Sept. 3 Died, Washington, D.C.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Joseph L. Rauh, Jr. (1911-1992), span the years 1913-2008, with the majority of the items concentrated between 1950 and 1984. The bulk of the papers documents Rauh's career as a public interest lawyer who handled cases pertaining chiefly to civil rights, civil liberties, and labor disputes. Also interfiled throughout the collection are a few papers of his law partners, John Silard and Elliott C. Lichtman. There are five parts and a restricted portion.
Part I of the Rauh Papers consist of eight series: Personal Correspondence, General Correspondence, Americans for Democratic Action File, Hubert H. Humphrey Campaign File, Subject File, Legal File, Appointment Books, and Miscellany.
Papers in the Personal Correspondence series, 1938-1988, and General Correspondence series, 1949-1980, consist of incoming and outgoing correspondence pertaining to Rauh's legal cases and to social and political issues that interested him, particularly civil rights, civil liberties, and labor. The General Correspondence pertains mostly to Rauh's legal cases, while the Personal Correspondence relates principally to his private interests. There is a great deal of similar material in both series, however, since he supported several causes both publicly and privately. Because the two series overlap, some of the same correspondents and many of the same topics appear in both. Each series includes correspondence between Rauh and his family, friends, acquaintances, and the general public, although family correspondence is limited and appears mostly in the early years of the Personal Correspondence series. Personal Correspondence files from 1946 to 1949 have indexes appearing at the beginning of each folder which list correspondents and, at times, topics. General Correspondence from 1973 to 1980 consists primarily of outgoing letters. The correspondence is filed in the same arrangement in which it was transferred to the Library.
The Americans for Democratic Action (ADA) File, 1949-1976, documents Rauh's activities as a member and officeholder of this political advocacy group. The papers document Rauh's activities as an organizer, public speaker, and fund-raiser. In addition, he testified about a wide variety of issues on ADA's behalf before many congressional committees. The papers further document Rauh's and the organization's position on civil rights, foreign and domestic policy, government loyalty/security measures, communism, civil liberties, national political campaigns, and other issues. Rauh and the ADA worked to defeat the attempt by Henry Wallace and his Progressive Party to assume the leadership of American liberalism in 1948. Rauh and the ADA were also active in moving civil rights to the center of the liberal agenda and in inserting a civil rights plank into the platform of the Democratic party. Rauh was also one of the first to object to the tactics used by Senator Joseph McCarthy and the House Un-American Activities Committee. The ADA files further reflect Rauh's efforts in behalf of civil rights and encouraging an anti-Vietnam War position within the Democratic party in 1967. Additional ADA-related correspondence appears in the Personal and General Correspondence files.
The Hubert H. Humphrey Campaign File, 1956-1963, pertains to Humphrey's unsuccessful 1960 presidential campaign. Rauh, vice chairman of the Democratic Central Committee in the District of Columbia in 1959-1960 and a close friend of Humphrey, campaigned actively on the senator's behalf. The papers relate primarily to Rauh's fund-raising activities and plans for campaign strategy.
Papers in the Subject File, 1944-1988, document Rauh's activities and interests in affirmative action, civil rights, civil liberties, labor issues, union democracy, politics, and other issues. The papers show Rauh's active support in the Democratic party for civil rights and party reform. In addition, they reflect his role in the formulation and enactment of civil rights legislation. There are files containing correspondence and material that Rauh used to oppose the Supreme Court nominations of Clement F. Haynsworth and G. Harrold Carswell. Also included are files pertaining to Rauh's unsuccessful fight against William H. Rehnquist's nomination to the Court and his subsequent elevation to chief justice. These papers also document Rauh's participation in attempts, 1950-1975, to curb the use of the filibuster in the Senate. Papers related to his support for home rule in the District of Columbia are located in the District of Columbia, Democratic Central Committee files.
The Legal File, 1948-1986, constitutes the majority of the collection and consist chiefly of case files of Rauh's clients. Many of these cases are public service ones in which Rauh defended underrepresented groups and interests. Most of the cases pertain to civil rights, rights of trade unions, such as the Brotherhood of Sleeping Car Porters and the United Auto Workers, abuses of the federal loyalty/security programs, and other civil liberties issues. Two of Rauh's notable clients were Lillian Hellman, whom he represented before the House Un-American Activities Committee, and the members of the Mississippi Freedom Democratic Party. For the latter he won a symbolic offer of two seats for the Freedom Party at the 1964 Democratic National Convention, thereby ending the seating of segregated delegations. A letter to Rauh from Arthur Miller in which Miller describes his reaction to Marilyn Monroe's death is located in Jacobo Muchnik's file. A large miscellany subseries is composed of briefs, writs, and congressional committee prints concerning cases that Rauh handled.
The final two series include Appointment Books, 1955-1986, and Miscellany, 1913-1988. The Appointment Books series consist of calendars recording Rauh's personal and business engagements. Papers in the Miscellany series are chiefly speeches, writings, interviews, and Rauh's letters to newspaper and magazine editors concerning his positions on various legal, political, and social issues.
Part II, a 1989 addition to the Rauh Papers, consists chiefly of correspondence and legal papers relating to Orlikow v. United States, a case in which Rauh represented Velma Orlikow and eight other defendants who were brainwashed without their knowledge or consent at the Allan Memorial Institute in Montreal, Canada. Experiments were performed on the patients by psychiatrist Ewen Cameron, who was funded from 1958 until 1960 by the Central Intelligence Agency (CIA).
Part III, a 1994 addition complementing Rauh's papers received in previous installments, includes personal correspondence, subject files, legal files, speeches, and writings. The subject files document Rauh's activities and interests in civil rights, politics, and the Supreme Court. Almost all of the legal files relate to Orlikow v. United States.
Part IV, a 1999 addition, also supplements previous installments of the Rauh Papers and includes personal correspondence, subject files, legal files, oral history interviews, speeches, writings, and letters of condolence to Rauh's wife, Olie, upon his death in 1992. The subject files relate primarily to Rauh's interest in civil rights and the Supreme Court. Wage and hour legislation files from 1939 to 1942 chronicle Rauh's service as counsel to the Department of Labor. Prominent correspondents in Part IV include Benjamin N. Cardozo, Benjamin V. Cohen, and Felix Frankfurter.
Part V, a 2015 addition, features some topics and time periods common to other parts of the Rauh Papers. It includes correspondence, legal files, speeches and writings, family papers, oral history interviews, press and magazine articles about Rauh, and files relating to his death. The majority of the addition relates to correspondence and legal papers pertaining to Rauh's client, William Walter Remington. Rauh defended Remington against charges of perjury resulting from his denial under oath that he had participated in a Soviet espionage ring and that he had been a member of the Communist Party. Remington was convicted of perjury and murdered in prison. The correspondence also includes some letters to Rauh's wife, Olie Westheimer Rauh.
Other prominent and frequent correspondents in the collection include Carl A. Auerbach, William J. Brennan (1906-1997), Paul H. Douglas, Felix Frankfurter, Jack Greenberg, Aaron Henry, Edward D. Hollander, Hubert H. Humphrey, Lyndon B. Johnson, Edward M. Kennedy, James I. Loeb, Eugene J. McCarthy, Walter Reuther, Eleanor Roosevelt, Arthur Meier Schlesinger (1917- ), James A. Wechsler, Roy Wilkins, and Joseph Yablonski.
Organization of the Papers
The collection is arranged in five parts composed of eighteen series. Also includes a restricted portion:
Part I:
Personal Correspondence, 1938-1988
General Correspondence, 1949-1980
Americans for Democratic Action File, 1949-1976
Hubert H. Humphrey Campaign File, 1956-1963
Subject File, 1944-1988
Legal File, 1940-1986
Appointment Books, 1955-1986
Miscellany, 1913-1989
Part II: 1989 Addition
Legal File, 1926-1988
Part III: 1994 Addition:
Personal Correspondence, 1966-1992
Subject File, 1928-1992.
Legal File, 1949-1990
Miscellany, 1940-1992
Part IV: 1999 Addition
Personal Correspondence, 1984-1986
Subject File, 1928-1993
Legal File, 1985-1994
Miscellany, 1940-1993
Part V: 2015 Addition
Restricted
Container List
- Part I: Personal Correspondence, 1938-1988 (Box 1-4)
  Correspondence and memoranda between Rauh and his family, friends, acquaintances, and the public documenting Rauh's public and personal interests.
  Rauh's arrangement for the years 1938-1972 was reverse chronological order, and correspondence from 1973 to 1985 was arranged chronologically by a group of years and then alphabetically. For example, correspondence for the years 1973-1976 is arranged in reverse chronological order as one group and then filed alphabetically by name of correspondent.
  - 1984-1988 (Box 1)
  - 1981-1983, (4 folders)
  - 1977-1980
    - A-G, (3 folders)
    - H-Z, (4 folders) (Box 2)
  - 1973-1976
    - A-J, (4 folders)
    - K-Z, (7 folders) (Box 3)
  - 1961-1972
  - 1952-1960
  - Apr. 1947-May 1949
  - Feb. 1946-Mar. 1947 (Box 4)
  - Aug. 1938-Jan. 1946, undated
- Part I: General Correspondence, 1949-1980 (Box 4-11)
  Correspondence and memoranda between Rauh and his friends, acquaintances, family, clients, and the public pertaining to legal matters and social and political interests, particularly labor, labor unions, civil rights, and civil liberties.
  Correspondence for the years 1973 to 1980 is arranged in reverse chronological order. Correspondence from 1949 to 1972 is arranged alphabetically as received by the first letter of the correspondent's last name and then by year in reverse chronological order.
  - 1980, (4 folders) (Box 4)
  - 1979
    - July-Dec.
    - Jan.-June (Box 5)
  - 1978, (2 folders)
  - 1977, (3 folders)
  - 1976, (3 folders) (Box 6)
  - 1975, (4 folders)
  - 1974
    - Oct.-Dec.
    - Jan.-Sept., (3 folders) (Box 7)
  - 1973, (4 folders)
  - 1949-1972 (Box 8)
    - A-E, (9 folders)
    - F-M, (10 folders) (Box 9)
  - 1949-1972 (Box 10)
    - M-S, (10 folders)
    - T-Z, (6 folders) (Box 11)
- Part I: Americans for Democratic Action File, 1949-1976 (Box 11-17)
  Correspondence, memoranda, minutes of meetings, reports, speeches, press releases, pamphlets, financial and policy statements, lists of members, resolutions, newspaper clippings, and other printed matter pertaining to Rauh's activities in ADA.
  Arranged as received in reverse chronological order.
  - 1964-1976, undated, (7 folders) (Box 11)
  - 1958-1963, (7 folders) (Box 12)
  - 1957
    - July-Dec.
    - Jan.-June (Box 13)
  - 1956
    - Apr.-Dec., (5 folders)
    - Jan.-Mar., (2 folders) (Box 14)
  - 1955
    - May-Dec., (4 folders)
    - Jan.-Apr. (Box 15)
  - 1953-1954, (4 folders)
  - 1952, (3 folders) (Box 16)
  - 1951
    - Apr.-Dec., (3 folders)
    - Jan.-Mar. (Box 17)
  - 1949-1950, (8 folders)
- Part I: Hubert H. Humphrey Campaign File, 1956-1963 (Box 18-20)
  Correspondence, memoranda, press releases, speeches, photographs, pamphlets, programs, reports, invitations, newspaper clippings, and other material documenting Rauh's role in Humphrey's 1960 presidential campaign.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of person or organization, topic, or type of material. Papers within each folder are arranged as received in reverse chronogical order.
  - Correspondence (Box 18)
    - General, 1959-1963, (5 folders)
    - Thank-you letters, 1959
  - District of Columbia Committee, 1959-1960, (2 folders)
  - Finances, 1960
  - History, 1956-1961
  - Memoranda, 1959-1960 (Box 19)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1959-1960
  - Speeches
    - Draft, 1959-1960
    - Given
      - May 1959-Apr. 1960, (3 folders)
      - Dec. 1958-Apr. 1959 (Box 20)
    - Reference, 1959-1960
  - Symington, Stuart, 1960
  - Uncommitted electors, 1959-1960
  - Ziffren Committee, 1959-1960
- Part I: Subject File, 1944-1988 (Box 20-45)
  Correspondence, memoranda, legal briefs and writs, reports, minutes of meetings, newspaper clippings, printed matter, and other material concerning Rauh's activities and interests in civil rights, civil liberties, labor issues, politics, and other issues.
  Arranged alphabetically as received by name of individual or organization, topic, or type of material.
  - Affirmative action (Box 20)
    - 1984-1985, (2 folders)
    - 1977-1980, (4 folders) (Box 21)
    - 1972-1976, (4 folders) (Box 22)
  - American Civil Liberties Union, 1951-1970
  - Antioch University, Yellow Springs, Ohio, 1966-1985, (2 folders)
  - Atomic energy (Box 23)
    - Emergency conference for civilian control, 1946, (2 folders)
    - International control, 1946
  - Auerbach, Carl A., 1958-1968
  - Bell, Griffin B., attorney general nomination
    - General, 1977
    - Hearings, 1977
    - Newspaper clippings, 1976-1977
  - Bork, Robert, and Ginsberg, Douglas H., Supreme Court nominations, 1987
  - Capital punishment, 1961-1967 (Box 24)
  - Cardozo, Benjamin N., 1957-1967
  - Carswell, G. Harrold, Supreme Court nomination
    - Clippings, 1970
    - General, 1970-1971
  - Civil rights See also Container 269, same heading
    - Albany, Ga., 1963
    - General
      - 1960-1985, (6 folders)
      - 1959, (3 folders) (Box 25)
    - Grant-in-aid, 1963
    - United States Congress, August session, 1960
  - Civil Rights Act
    - 1966
    - Feb.-Dec. 1958
    - Aug. 1957-Jan. 1958 (Box 26)
    - 1956-1957, (2 folders)
  - Civil rights acts, 1963-1965
  - Civil rights acts and Voting Rights Act, amendments, 1981
  - Civil rights and civil liberties, 1952-1957, 1964-1965, (3 folders)
  - Commission on Government Security, 1957
  - Commission on Social Action, 1958-1964
  - Conflict of interest, 1962-1967 (Box 27)
  - Congressional investigations, 1957-1962
  - Constitutional convention, 1966-1970
  - Copyrights, 1961
  - Council for a Livable World, 1962-1972, (4 folders)
  - County unit primary system, 1958-1959
  - Criminal practice, 1965-1966, 1981 (Box 28)
  - Defense Facilities Protection Act of 1954, 1954-1955
  - Democratic Party See also Container 270, same heading
    - Committee against Discrimination, 1965
    - Delegate challenge, Mississippi, 1972
    - Delegate selection, Mississippi, 1969-1971
    - Delegate selection and party organization, 1969-1975, (5 folders) (Box 29)
    - Democratic National Convention
      - 1968
        - Credentials contest
          - General, 1968, (2 folders)
          - Mississippi, 1967-1968
      - 1964
      - 1960
      - 1956
    - Democratic Peace Caucus, 1967-1968, (3 folders) (Box 30)
    - District of Columbia
      - Central Committee
        - Certification of job seekers, 1961-1967, (5 folders)
        - General (Box 31)
          - 1961-1966, (6 folders)
          - 1948-1960 (Box 32)
        - Home rule, 1965-1971
        - Minutes of meetings, 1960-1967, (2 folders)
        - Primary, 1964
          - Contributions and bills
          - General, (2 folders)
          - Statements, reports, and memoranda (Box 33)
          - Miscellany
        - Rauh's resignation, 1967
      - McCarthy, Eugene J., for President, 1968
    - General, 1980-1981
    - Mississippi, 1978
    - Platforms, 1944-1972
  - District of Columbia Bar Association, 1961-1968
  - Douglas, Paul Howard, 1962, 1976
  - Eisenhower, Dwight D., 1948
  - Election reform and campaign financing, 1966-1967
  - Election registration bill, federal, 1960 (Box 34)
  - Election registration bill of 1959, federal, 1958-1959
  - Fair Employment Practices Bill, 1961-1963
  - Fair Employment Practices Commission, National Council for, 1945-1946
  - Federal Bureau of Investigation
    - Clippings, 1949-1951, 1958-1965
    - General, 1950-1951, 1957
  - Frankfurter, Felix
    - General, 1945-1948, 1956-1963
    - Portrait, 1973-1974
  - Ginsberg, Douglas H. See Container 23, same heading
  - Government security, Hubert H. Humphrey's Special Commission, 1955-1956 (Box 35)
  - Harriman, W. Averell, campaign for president, 1952
  - Haynsworth, Clement F., Supreme Court nomination, 1969-1970, (3 folders)
  - House Un-American Activities Committee, 1949, 1954-1957, 1968
  - Housing Expediter, Office of (Box 36)
    - General, 1946-1949, (2 folders)
    - Lustron Corp., 1946-1947, (2 folders)
    - Tucker Corp., 1947
  - Humphrey, Hubert H., 1964-1972 See also Container 271, same heading
  - Johnson, Lyndon B., 1948, 1958-1960, 1969
  - Jones, Lee, re William Remington book, 1978-1979, 1985 See also Container 271, same heading
  - Kennedy, Anthony, 1987-1988
  - Kennedy, Edward M., 1968-1971, 1980 (Box 37)
  - Kennedy, John F.
    - Administration, government positions, 1960-1961
    - General, 1958-1960, 1967
  - Labor Management Reporting and Disclosure Act of 1959, 1980
  - Lewis, Fulton, 1956
  - Lowenstein, Allard K., Richard Cummings book, 1985
  - Loyalty/security, 1947-1956, 1965, (4 folders)
  - McCarthy, Eugene J., 1968 (Box 38)
  - McCarthy, Joseph R., 1953-1954, (2 folders)
  - Marshall Plan, Committee to Aid European Recovery, 1947-1948
  - Modern Community Developers, 1958-1968
  - Morse, Wayne, reelection campaign, 1967-1968
  - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People, 1956-1974
  - National Council for Fair Employment Practices Commission See Container 34, Fair Employment Practices Commission
  - Nixon, Richard M., 1956
  - Passports